Preliminary Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Burkhard Schwarz Papers, circa 1973-1989
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Burkhard Schwarz papers circa 1973-1989
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office.
22.7 Linear Feet 17,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives. Frankfurt Office. Burkhard Schwarz Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1996.
Historical Note
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) was founded in New York, N.Y., in 1864, and is one of the world's largest advertising agencies. The company's Frankfurt Office was opened in 1952. Burkhard Schwarz was an advertising executive in the Frankfurt Office of the J. Walter Thompson Company in the 1970s and 1980s.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, personnel files, financial summaries, client files, and files of prospects and new business contacts that detail the business activities of the J. Walter Thompson Co.'s Frankfurt Office and Burkhard Schwarz's work there (17,000 items, 22.7 linear feet, ca. 1973-1989). Correspondence includes discussion of the company's reorganization in 1986 and attempts at collaboration with affiliated offices (e.g. Hill and Knowlton). Clients include Nestlé, Kodak, Burger King, Ford, Sunlicht, Elida, Kellogg, and DeBeers. Other material includes complete copies of lectures on business issues by JWT associates and others; JWT's 3 Year Plans (for the 1980s); and minutes and proceedings from European advertising symposia, both JWT specific (e.g. Managers Monthly Assessment, European Managers Meeting) and industry-wide (e.g. Davos, EPCOT). Most of the material is in German, but many files contain some English, especially correspondence with other JWT offices, symposia, and general JWT memoranda. Accessioned as part of the J. Walter Thompson Company, Frankfurt Office Records, 1959-1991 and undated (96-009). Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising, and Marketing History.
Processing note: This collection has not yet been fully processed and organized. Thus, box contents do not always reflect logical subject groupings.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Schwarz, Burkhard
J. Walter Thompson Company
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office
Hill and Knowlton, Inc
Nestlé.
Eastman Kodak Company
Burger King Corporation
Kellogg Company
De Beers Consolidated Mines
Advertising agencies
Advertising agencies -- Germany.
Advertising executives
Advertising -- Management.
Advertising -- History.
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Accession 1996-009
  Portions of this collection are restricted to use only by J. Walter Thompson staff. Consult a reference archivist for more information.
  - Contents of box 1: (Box 1)
    - Nestlé, 1980-1989, (4 folders)
    - Philips, 1979-1989, (4 folders)
    - Kodak, 1971, (3 folders)
    - Kodak, 1980-1989, (4 folders)
      [Notebooks of Christian Grupe]
    - DeBeers, Kellogg, 1970-1983, (3 folders)
    - Burger King, Ford, Sunlicht, Elida, 1970-1983, (2 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 2: (Box 2)
    - Burger King, Ford, Sunlicht, Elida, 1970-1983, (2 of 4 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients] K-Q, 1970-1983, (4 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients] R-Z, 1970-1983, (4 folders)
    - Seminare [Seminars], 1971-1975, (2 folders)
    - JWT Allgemein [General Information], 1974-1987, (4 folders)
    - JWT Office London, 1979-1983, (5 folders)
    - Agency Compensation, 1970-1985, (1 folder)
  - Contents of box 3: (Box 3)
    - New York, 1980-1989, (4 folders)
    - JWT Offices, Correspondence, A-Z, 1978, (4 folders)
    - Finanzen [Finances], 1977-1982, (4 folders)
    - Finance, 1986, (4 folders)
    - P [Personnel?]: Allgemein, Organisation, Etat, Bewerbung [General, Organization, Budget, Employment Application(s)], 1975-1976, (4 folders)
    - Annual Management Assessment, 1976-1980, (2 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 4: (Box 4)
    - Annual Management Assessment, 1976-1980, (2 of 4 folders)
    - Schotten Meetings, 1980-1981, (3 folders)
    - Basis Research, 1981-1987, (4 folders)
    - Markenplan VRBA, 1980-1981, (2 folders)
    - Markenplan: Verträge [Contracts], 1981, (2 folders)
    - Allgemein [General], 1976, (4 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], K-O, 1986, (3 folders)
    - Nestlé, 1985-1987, (2 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 5: (Box 5)
    - Nestlé, 1985-1987, (2 of 4 folders)
    - [Managers Monthly Assessment], 1984 August-1985 December, (4 folders)
    - Executive Board, AMG, OMG, 1986-1987, (1 folder)
    - JWT London, 1984, (2 folders)
    - JWT Office New York, 1979-1984, (4 folders)
    - Memoranda / Haus-Mitteilungen, 1977-1982 Correspondence, 1980, (4 folders)
    - MMA [Managers Monthly Assessment], 1981-1982, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 6: (Box 6)
    - MMA [Managers Monthly Assessment], 1979-1980, (4 folders)
    - EMM [European Managers Meeting], 1977-1987, (4 folders)
    - EMM [European Managers Meeting], 1983, (3 folders)
    - [European Managers Group] 1992 Group, 1989, (2 folders)
    - GC, GL, Directors Meeting, Creative Planboards, 1977-1985, (4 folders)
    - Klausurtagung Niederwald [Private Meeting], 1985, (2 folders)
    - FACHGLAS, GEFA, 1980-1989, (1 folder)
    - Future, 1980, (2 folders)
    - CLK [ Craton Lodge and Knight], 1986-1988, (1 folder)
  - Contents of box 7: (Box 7)
    - Vorträge--Allgemein [Lectures--General], 1985-1989, (4 folders)
    - Vorträge--Allgemein [Lectures--General], 1983-1984, (4 folders)
    - Vorträge--Allgemein [Lectures--General], 1977, (4 folders)
    - Andere [Other] Offices, 1978-1987, (3 folders)
    - JWT London, 1985-1986, (4 folders)
    - 3-Years Plan: Where are we, 1980-1982, (3 folders)
  - Contents of box 8: (Box 8)
    - Finanzen, Verträge [Finances, Contracts], 1983-1984, (3 folders)
    - Wien [ Vienna]: 3-Years Plan, Finance, Personal, Pension / Versicherung [Insurance], Taxes, 1983-1987, (3 folders)
    - Presse [Media], 1985, (3 folders)
    - Euro-Ad, 1978-1985, (3 folders)
    - EROC [JWT Regional Meeting], 1986, (4 folders)
    - Korrespondenz Allgemein [General Correspondence], 1981-1984, (4 of 5 folders)
  - Contents of box 9: (Box 9)
    - Korrespondenz Allgemein [General Correspondence], 1981-1984, (1 of 5 folders)
    - Releases, Newsletter, 1979-1986, (4 folders)
    - GWA Korrespondenz [Correspondence], 1985-1986, (3 folders)
    - GWA: Korrespondenz [Correspondence], 1987-1988, (3 folders)
    - GWA: Sitzungen, Protokolle [Meetings, Minutes], 1987-1988, (4 folders)
    - Vorträge [Lectures], 1985, (3 folders)
    - Vorträge [Lectures]: allg. [gen.], Sunlicht, 1976-1978, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 10: (Box 10)
    - JWT Allgemein [General], 1988-1990, (4 folders)
    - JWT [Directories], 1980-1989, (1 folder)
    - MMA [Managers Monthly Assessment], 1988, (4 folders)
    - Privat, Management Wechsel [Personal, Change in Management], 1971-1977, (3 folders)
    - Annual Management Assessment, 1980-1981, (2 folders)
    - Davos [Symposium], 1979-1986, (5 folders)
    - TandA; Deltakos, 1978-1988, (3 folders)
    - Acquisitions, Mergers; Proposal Düsseldorf; Future Speech, 1985-1990, (1 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 11: (Box 11)
    - Acquisitions, Mergers; Proposal Düsseldorf; Future Speech, 1985-1990, (3 of 4 folders)
    - Düsseldorf, 1985-1989, (3 folders)
    - Client Retention [includes Christian Grupe files], 1986-1989, (3 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], A-E, 1988-1989, (6 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], K-O, 1988-1989, (3 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], S-Z, 1988-1989, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 12: (Box 12)
    - GWA Korrespondenz [Correspondence], 1989-1990, (3 folders)
    - GWA Sitzungen / Protokolle [Meetings / Minutes], 1989, (2 folders)
    - H and K [ Hill and Knowlton], 1980-1984, (3 folders)
    - Basis, H and K, Conquest, Business World, T and A, 1986-1990, (2 folders)
    - JWT Direct, 1985-1988, (3 folders)
    - Düsseldorf Bürogründung / Opening, 1982-1983, (2 folders)
    - Hamburg, JWT Direct, Düsseldorf, WPP, 1983-1989, (5 folders)
    - Hamburg Kunden [Clients], NB [New Business], 1980-1988, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 13: (Box 13)
    - Zürich bis 1988, 1979-1988, (4 folders)
    - H. F. Peters, 1981-1988, (2 folders)
    - Personal, 1985-1989, (3 folders)
    - Personal A-O, Allg. Bewerb. [General and Employment Applications], 1973-1985, (3 folders)
    - Personal P-Z, Allg. Bewerb. [General and Employment Applications], 1973-1985, (3 folders)
    - Kellogg, 1988, (3 folders)
    - Ford Client Retention, 1979-1986, (1 folder)
    - Ford Korrespondenz [Correspondence], 1983-1988, (2 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 14: (Box 14)
    - Ford Korrespondenz [Correspondence], 1983-1988, (2 of 4 folders)
    - Ford, 1985-1986, (9 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], A-J, bis Ende 1983, 1976-1983, (4 folders)
    - Bacardi, 1988, (3 folders)
    - Kellogg, 1984-1987, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 15: (Box 15)
    - Sunlicht Coordination, 1973-1977, (3 folders)
    - Burger King, 1983-1986, (1 folder)
    - DeBeers, 1983-1987, (1 folder)
    - Kunden [Clients], A-J, 1984-1987, (3 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], K-M, 1986-1988, (2 folders)
    - Pizza Hut, 1987-1988, (1 folder)
    - Kunden [Clients], P-R, 1984-1987, (3 folders)
    - Kunden [Clients], S-Z, 1984-1988, (1 folder)
    - Client Retention, 1981-1986, (4 of 5 folders)
  - Contents of box 16: (Box 16)
    - Client Retention, 1981-1986, (1 of 5 folders)
    - Finance, 1987, (4 folders)
    - EMG [Meetings], 1987-1988, (3 folders)
    - Korresp. Allgemein [Correspondence], 1983-1990, (4 folders)
    - Memos, 1984-1987, (3 folders)
    - WPP, 1986-1988, (3 folders)
    - EPCOT [World Advertising Forum], 1984, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 17: (Box 17)
    - Davos [World Economic Forum], 1986-1989, (3 folders)
    - London, 1987-1988, (3 folders)
    - New York [Correspondence], 1987-1988, (3 folders)
    - Wien [ Vienna], [ Tiefenbrunner], 1984-1986, (3 folders)
    - Direct Marketing, 1984-1985, (2 folders)
    - New York and Other Offices, 1989, (3 folders)
    - Hamburg, 1981-1987, (5 folders)
    - Wien [ Vienna], 1980-1987, (2 of 4 folders)
  - Contents of box 18: (Box 18)
    - Wien [ Vienna], 1980-1987, (2 of 4 folders)
    - Wien [ Vienna], 1987-1989, (4 folders)
    - Bacardi, 1985-1987, (4 folders)
    - Kellogg, 1987-1990, (4 folders)
    - Lever, 1982-1987, (3 folders)
    - Unilever, Elida, 1983-1989, (4 folders)
    - Acquisitions, 1985-1989, (1 folder)
  - Contents of box 19: (Box 19)
    - Umstrukturierung [Restructuring], 1986, (2 folders)
    - 3 Year Plan, 1983-1987, (3 folders)
    - NB Protokolle [New Business Minutes], 1987, (4 folders)
    - NB International [New Business], 1987-1989, (3 folders)
    - New Business, A-O, 1987, (3 folders)
    - New Business, P-Z, 1987, (4 folders)
    - New Business, S [Workshop], 1987-1989, (4 folders)
  - Contents of box 20: (Box 20)
    - NB [New Business], A-Z, 1989, (4 folders)
    - NB Kontakte [New Business Contacts], A-K, 1988-1989, (4 folders)
    - NB Kontakte [New Business Contacts], L-Z, 1988-1989, (3 folders)
    - Promotions, 1983-1984, (2 folders)
    - DeBeers, 1988, (4 folders)
    - DeBeers, 1989-1990, (4 folders)
    - Jacobs, 1984-1987, (5 folders)
  - Contents of box 21: (Box 21)
    - Jacobs, 1988-1989, (4 folders)
    - Pharma-Präsentationen [Pharmaceutical Presentations], 1978-1984, (5 folders)